<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: maps | John Beieler]]></title>
  <link href="http://johnb30.github.com/blog/categories/maps/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://johnb30.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-07-16T09:55:59-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://johnb30.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[John Beieler]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mapping Protest Data]]></title>
    <link href="http://johnb30.github.com/blog/2013/07/03/mapping-protest-data/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-03T16:03:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://johnb30.github.com/blog/2013/07/03/mapping-protest-data</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>GDELT and Protests</h3>

<p>Given the recent spate of protests around the world, there was some discussion
between <a href="http://dartthrowingchimp.wordpress.com/">Jay Ulfelder</a>,
<a href="https://www.utdallas.edu/~pxb054000/pbrandt/Home.html">Patrick Brandt</a>,
<a href="http://www.kalevleetaru.com/">Kalev Leetaru</a>,
<a href="http://eventdata.psu.edu/">Phil Schrodt</a>, and myself about the possibility of using
<a href="http://gdelt.utdallas.edu/">GDELT</a> to examine some of
the protest activity. Much of this still remains in the discussion stage, but
some data was pulled from GDELT, and I decided to venture into the world of
map making. As a caveat, I've never really worked with geographic visualization
of data, and this is my first cut at this type of work. So, without further
ado, the map is located at <a href="http://cdb.io/14RHla0">http://cdb.io/14RHla0</a>.</p>

<h3>Data</h3>

<p>The data used to create the map contains all CAMEO codes that begin with <code>14</code>,
which is the general category for "protest" events, for the year 2013. Including
data from earlier than 2013 made the map much too cluttered.
A potential issue with the use of this CAMEO category is that it picks up governments protesting other governments, politicians protesting
policies, etc. Thus why the U.S. is blank; it was a shining beacon of protest
activity that distracted from the other parts of the map. If anyone is
interested I can put the U.S. data back in and regenerate the map. The data
was grouped by the latitude and longitude coordinates, and a count of protest
events at each location is included. If you zoom in, you are able to see the
individuals points, which when clicked provide information about the location
and number of events.</p>

<p>The main takeaway from this map seems to be that GDELT does a pretty good job
of capturing the broad trends of protest activity; the areas that are "bright"
are those that would generally be expected to be so.</p>

<h3>Note on Tools</h3>

<p>The map was created using the fantastic <a href="http://cartodb.com/">CartoDB</a> along with CSS provided
by <a href="http://www.joshuastevens.net/">Josh Stevens</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
