<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: GDELT | John Beieler]]></title>
  <link href="http://johnb30.github.com/blog/categories/gdelt/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://johnb30.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-11-23T19:09:56-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://johnb30.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[John Beieler]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Noise in GDELT]]></title>
    <link href="http://johnb30.github.com/blog/2013/10/28/noise-and-gdelt/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-28T17:56:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://johnb30.github.com/blog/2013/10/28/noise-and-gdelt</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>The Signal and The Noise</h3>

<p>One of the first things that I tell people about <a href="http://gdelt.utdallas.edu/">GDELT</a> is that it is messy and noisy. This is not meant to be a dig
at the dataset. This is just a reality of dealing with data on this scale that is generated by automated processes
with little to no human supervision. One resulting aspect of this noisiness is a potentially high rate of false positives.
Mike Ward and crew recently authored a <a href="http://predictiveheuristics.com/2013/10/17/gdelt-and-icews-a-short-comparison/">blog post</a>
comparing GDELT data against ICEWS data. One conclusion of the
post is that there are a high number of false positives contained in GDELT. The flip side of this, however, is that
GDELT likely has a lower number of false negatives than other datasets; GDELT likely captures more events that actually
happen.</p>

<h3>Reducing the Noise</h3>

<p>One feature of GDELT that many people don’t know about, or don’t understand, is that full-text coding is utilized, i.e.,
an entire news article is coded, versus the lead sentence or paragraph (root) coding used by previous projects. There is
some <a href="http://cmp.sagepub.com/content/30/4/335.abstract">debate</a> about whether full-text coding provides additional, valuable information. For the purposes of this
post I assume that there <strong>is</strong> additional value added by full-text coding. The important point, however, is that
full-text coding likely adds more noise into the dataset by picking up things such as background information that is
often reported in news articles. For those who aren’t familiar, news articles often follow a set format with the
lead paragraph purposefully designed to provide the majority of the information about a news article. By focusing
only on the leads, though, it is possible to miss some additional information about related events. In short,
there is a tradeoff between full-text and root coding. Before discussing which type of coding
is better for various situations, I’d like to provide a bit of information as to the empirical distribution
of root and non-root events in GDELT.</p>

<h3>Analysis</h3>

<p>The GDELT dataset helpfully provides a variable, <code>IsRootEvent</code>, that indicates whether or not a coded event
occurs within the lead paragraph of a news story. For the purposes of this analysis, I replicate the
data used in the <a href="http://predictiveheuristics.com/2013/10/17/gdelt-and-icews-a-short-comparison/">blog post</a>
 by Mike Ward that was mentioned above (thanks to <a href="http://mattdickenson.com/">Matt Dickenson</a> for
providing the exact queries used). The data covers 2011-01-01 to 2012-09-03, with protest events pulled
for Egypt and Turkey and violent events pulled for Syria. There are 364,492 total events within the dataset.
The figure below gives comparison of the number root and non-root events
contained in the data.</p>

<p><img src="/blog/downloads/root_events/root_plot.png"></p>

<p>In addition to the above bar plot, the stacked time-series plot below shows the ratio of root to
non-root events over time.</p>

<p><img src="/blog/downloads/root_events/root_time_series.png"></p>

<p>Again, it is important to remember that journalistic practice almost
ensures that background information is given in later paragraphs. This means that review sentences such
as “over 10,000 have been killed over the past few months in Syria” tend to appear in this area. This
leads me to believe that some of the spikes seen in non-root events over time are a result
of these background sentences. With that said, there can also be events in the body of a news
story that might not be captured in other stories. To reiterate, there is a tradeoff between keeping and ignoring
these stories.</p>

<p>As a final view, the below map shows non-root events (red) vs. root events (blue). The purple dots are
created from overlaying the two event types on top of each other; purple dots indicate
areas that have coverage from both the root and non-root events. From even a cursory glance at this
map it seems that neither event type has a privilege on coverage. The two types of events agree on
many of the locations, and there is no systematic pattern in the areas where the two event types
do not agree. Thus, it seems that one can safely utilize only the root events without sacrificing
a significant amount of geographical coverage.</p>

<iframe width='100%' height='400' frameborder='0' src='http://johnb30.cartodb.com/viz/c3fd9b64-3da8-11e3-b928-3085a9a956e8/embed_map?title=true&description=true&search=false&shareable=true&cartodb_logo=true&layer_selector=true&legends=false&scrollwheel=true&sublayer_options=1%7C1&sql=SELECT%20*%20FROM%20root_map%20where%20root%20%3D%20true&sw_lat=24.06151244228118&sw_lon=13.3428955078125&ne_lat=41.979910896912486&ne_lon=55.5303955078125'></iframe>


<h3>Wrapping Up</h3>

<p>To get to the heart of the matter: if you’re worried about false positives, then filter the GDELT
data based on root events. Filtering in this manner shouldn’t cause that great of an information
loss. Note, however, that this filtering also <strong>won’t</strong> give you a completely clean, noiseless
dataset. The data is just more likely to have a reduced level of noise. On the flip side, if you’re more
worried about attempting to capture <strong>everything</strong> that happened, then make use of the entire dataset.</p>

<h3>Tools, data, etc.</h3>

<p>The map was made using the awesome tools provided by <a href="http://cartodb.com/">CartoDB</a>. The stacked area plot was created
using <a href="https://github.com/wrobstory/vincent">Vincent</a>, a Python wrapper for the Vega Javascript package. The code is available as an
<a href="https://gist.github.com/johnb30/7197680">IPython notebook</a>.</p>

<p>The base data is available <a href="/blog/downloads/root_events/root_events_analysis.csv.zip">here</a>,
while the data used when making the map is available <a href="/blog/downloads/root_events/root_map.csv.zip">here</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Week of Egyptian Protests]]></title>
    <link href="http://johnb30.github.com/blog/2013/08/19/week-of-egyptian-protests/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-19T11:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://johnb30.github.com/blog/2013/08/19/week-of-egyptian-protests</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>Egypt Is Burning</h3>

<p><a href="http://www.kalevleetaru.com/">Kalev Leetaru</a> pointed out to me that the
recent events in Egypt would provide another opportunity to visualize the
<a href="http://gdelt.utdallas/edu">GDELT</a> data and how it tracks the protests.
In addition, GDELT also provides the opportunity to track the government
response to the protests. My <a href="http://johnbeieler.org/protest_mapping">previous</a>
<a href="http://http://johnbeieler.org/blog/2013/07/03/mapping-protest-data/">maps</a>
only examined the presence of protest behavior across the world. For this set
of maps, however, I focus instead on Egypt alone and include various
government responses to the protest activity.</p>

<h3>The Data</h3>

<p>As always, the data is pulled from the GDELT dataset. The data runs from
August 9th until the 17th, which I've used to create two separate maps. With each of
these maps, in the upper right corner you can choose the layers that appear
on the map. When both layers appear on the map, the clickable points show the
information <strong>only</strong> for the protest events. If you disable the protest layer,
you can see information for the additional violence or posture levels. Each
point includes a record of number of events, location name, and the source
URLs used to generate the events. As a note, CartoDB doesn't play nicely with
the long string of source URLs, so each URL is only separated by a space and
must be copied and pasted into a browser. Finally, it is important to note
that zooming in on the map is highly suggested; the GDELT dataset provides
a fair amount of city-level detail in the geolocation of events and it is
very interesting to see the spread of protests and government responses.</p>

<p>The first map displays protest behavior, subsetted from GDELT using root CAMEO
codes of <code>14</code>, with an overlay of violent events as red circles. The violent
events are pulled using the root CAMEO code of <code>18</code>, with the additional
stipulation that the target of the action had to be civilian in some way,
as indicated by a <code>CVL</code> label in one of the <code>Actor2Type</code> codes. This generates
the following map:</p>

<iframe width='100%' height='400' frameborder='0' src='http://johnb30.cartodb.com/viz/1c551484-0868-11e3-bae6-3085a9a956e8/embed_map?title=true&description=true&search=false&shareable=false&cartodb_logo=true&layer_selector=true&legends=false&scrollwheel=true&sublayer_options=1%7C1&sql=&sw_lat=23.65349807460049&sw_lon=18.194046020507812&ne_lat=33.09054478515459&ne_lon=46.31904602050781'></iframe>


<p>The second map uses the same protest data, but instead overlays CAMEO root
codes of <code>15</code>, which indicates a change in military or police posture.
This results in</p>

<iframe width='100%' height='400' frameborder='0' src='http://johnb30.cartodb.com/viz/ec0402a2-0869-11e3-86d4-3085a9a956e8/embed_map?title=true&description=true&search=false&shareable=false&cartodb_logo=true&layer_selector=true&legends=true&scrollwheel=true&sublayer_options=1%7C1&sql=&sw_lat=23.80544961231464&sw_lon=19.1162109375&ne_lat=33.22949814144951&ne_lon=47.2412109375'></iframe>


<p>I leave the substantive interpretation up to the reader, but it is worthwhile
to note that the change in military/police posture events are more widespread
than the violent events. As expected, there is also a high concentration of
violent events within Cairo.</p>

<h3>Tools</h3>

<p>As with the previous maps, I made use of the great tools developed by
<a href="http://cartodb.com/">CartoDB</a> and CSS by
<a href="http://www.joshuastevens.net/">Josh Stevens</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Animated Protest Mapping]]></title>
    <link href="http://johnb30.github.com/blog/2013/07/31/animated-protest-mapping/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-31T21:20:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://johnb30.github.com/blog/2013/07/31/animated-protest-mapping</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of the primary shortcomings of the original
<a href="http://johnb30.cartodb.com/viz/ffd5eeb6-ee20-11e2-8fd0-3085a9a956e8/embed_map?title=false&amp;description=true&amp;search=false&amp;shareable=false&amp;cartodb_logo=true&amp;layer_selector=false&amp;scrollwheel=true&amp;sublayer_options=1&amp;sql=&amp;zoom=2&amp;center_lat=-0.004273915238222043&amp;center_lon=-8.0859375">protest map</a>
I posted was that it only captured a static picture of protest activity over
a 6 month span. While this was interesting in its own right, many people,
including myself, were interested in how protest behavior changes over time.
Given this, I decided to explore creating an animated version of the original
protest map.</p>

<h3>Data</h3>

<p>As I've mentioned before, the <a href="http://gdelt.utdallas.edu">GDELT data</a> covers
from 1979 until present day, with continuous daily updates. I'm making use of
a subset that runs through June of 2013. The same caveats of the data
that I noted in the
<a href="http://johnbeieler.org/blog/2013/07/03/mapping-protest-data/">previous post</a>
about the protest map still apply. When dealing with the time-series of data,
however, one additional, and very important, point also applies. The number
of events recorded in GDELT grows exponentially over time, as noted in the
<a href="http://gdelt.utdallas.edu/data/documentation/ISA.2013.GDELT.pdf">paper</a>
introducing the dataset. This means that over time there appears to be a
steady increase in events, but this should not be mistaken as a rise in the
actual amount of behavior <code>X</code> (protest behavior in this case). Instead, due
to changes in reporting and the digital recording of news stories, it is
simply the case that there are more events of every type over time. In some
preliminary work that is not yet publicly released, protest behavior seems to
remain relatively constant over time as a <strong>percentage</strong> of the total number
of events. This means that while there was an explosion of protest activity
in the Middle East, and elsewhere, during the past few years, identifying
visible patterns is a tricky endeavor due to the nature of the underlying data.</p>

<p>Finally, the data used to create the map can be viewed
<a href="https://johnb30.cartodb.com/tables/protest_data/">here</a>. In order to reduce
the data to a manageable size, only locations where 10 or more events occurred
within a specific month are included. 10 events is an admittedly arbitrary cutoff,
but given that the highest number of events for one location in a
given month is 3,746 (Cairo in February of 2011) I feel that it is reasonable.</p>

<h3>The Map</h3>

<p>With these notes out of the way, the map can be viewed at
<a href="http://johnbeieler.org/protest_mapping">johnbeieler.org/protest_mapping</a>.
The color of each point is scaled by the number of events, with darker circles
indicating more events.</p>

<h3>Tools, etc.</h3>

<p>Once again this map was made using the wonderful tools provided by
<a href="http://cartodb.com">CartoDB</a>. For the animation specifically, I made use of
the <a href="https://github.com/CartoDB/torque">Torque</a> library provided by CartoDB.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Protest Behavior and Ramadan]]></title>
    <link href="http://johnb30.github.com/blog/2013/07/16/protest-behavior-and-ramadan/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-16T18:54:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://johnb30.github.com/blog/2013/07/16/protest-behavior-and-ramadan</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>Plotting Protests</h3>

<p>There's been a fair amount of <a href="http://worldnews.nbcnews.com/_news/2013/07/13/19439120-fasting-makes-us-stronger-cairo-protesters-carry-on-despite-ramadan?lite">discussion</a>
 in the <a href="http://www.dw.de/protests-in-turkey-continue-despite-ramadan/a-16943978">news</a>
<a href="http://world.time.com/2013/07/12/egypts-crisis-ramadan-heat-cools-tensions-in-cairo-for-now/">media</a>
recently about whether the start of Ramadan will lead to a decrease in protest
behavior in locations such as Egypt and Turkey. While I don't
have a forecast to offer, I do have data from <a href="http://gdelt.utdallas.edu">GDELT</a>
that tracks protest activity dating back to 1979. With the help of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Ramadan100years1938-2037.png">Wikipedia</a>
I was able to identify the beginning of Ramadan going back to 1979. Using
these dates, it is then possible to plot the time series of protest behavior
with the Ramadan time period layered on top. It is important to note that
this is a rather quick and dirty analysis. For example, in 1981 Ramadan began
on July 3 so I marked July and August as Ramadan months. It shouldn't affect
the visualization all that much, but I thought it is important to note. Taken
together, this data produces the following plot (larger version available
<a href="/blog/downloads/protest_plot.png">here</a>):</p>

<p><img src="/blog/downloads/protest_plot.png"></p>

<p>A quick eyeball test seems to indicate that Ramadan often coincides with a
slightly lower level of protest activity over time. In order to shore
this up, a quick correlation of "Ramadan" with the protest data shows a
coefficient of about <code>-0.025</code>, which indicates a very weak, negative
relationship between Ramadan and protest behavior.</p>

<h3>Caveats, notes, etc.</h3>

<p>With this said, it is important to note a few things about the data. First,
this includes <strong>all</strong> protest activity over time. Events such
as the US protesting the behavior of another state are included along with
civilian protests. This data also includes protest data
from the entire globe; it is quite possible that the effects of Ramadan are
more pronounced in countries with a higher Muslim population.
A final issue is the possible presence of seasonality in the data. Ramadan
just might happen to coincide with time periods that
experience lower protest activity, e.g., the summer months.</p>

<h3>Data</h3>

<p>Since I complained on Twitter that the creators of time-series plots often fail
to upload the data used to create the time series, the
protest data is available <a href="/blog/downloads/protest_data.csv">here</a>, while the
dates for Ramadan I used are <a href="/blog/downloads/ramadan_dates.csv">here</a>.
As a final note on the data, the values for the protests are percentages of
total events that occurred in a given month. This controls for
fact that later years, particularly those after 2005 or so, have more events
due to changes in reporting, etc.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mapping Protest Data]]></title>
    <link href="http://johnb30.github.com/blog/2013/07/03/mapping-protest-data/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-03T16:03:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://johnb30.github.com/blog/2013/07/03/mapping-protest-data</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Edit July 17, 2013:</em></p>

<p>Since this map got picked up by the <a href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/news/datablog/interactive/2013/jul/17/global-map-protests-2013">Guardian</a>,
I thought I would clarify some points further for those who aren't familiar with the data.</p>

<p>First, the GDELT data is based on news reports
from a variety of sources (a list of sources used can be found <a href="http://gdelt.utdallas.edu/about.html">here</a> under "Data Sources"). For
better or for worse, journalistic accounts of events are about the best we can do for large-scale, global projects such as this. Second,
if an event occurs but does not have a specific location within a country, e.g., "Protestors in Syria…", the event is geolocated to the
centroid of the country. This means that there may be some odd events at some locations, and with a high number of events. Third, the
"Event Count" featured on the map is the number of protest events that occurred at that location for the entire first half of 2013. This
means that if the "Event Count" variable shows 60, then there were 60 unique protest events at that location. This is not a measure of
scale or intensity of a given protest, or even how many times a certain protest was mentioned in the news media, though GDELT does record
this, it is simply a measure of unique events. Next, geolocation is hard, especially on the scale GDELT works on (300+ million events spanning
over 30 years), so some of the points may not be perfect. Even if 10 million events are located in the wrong place, however, that's still an error
rate of about 3%. Finally, and this is mentioned in the post further below, GDELT uses the <a href="http://gdelt.utdallas.edu/data/documentation/CAMEO.Manual.1.1b3.pdf">CAMEO</a>
coding scheme to classify events. This means that many different types of protest behavior are recorded, not just the protests or riots that come
to mind when one thinks of Egypt or Turkey. Russia verbally protesting actions of the United States is a protest event. This means that there
are both a higher number of events, and events that occur in locations that a person might not tie to a protest or riot.</p>

<h3>GDELT and Protests</h3>

<p>Given the recent spate of protests around the world, there was some discussion
between <a href="http://dartthrowingchimp.wordpress.com/">Jay Ulfelder</a>,
<a href="https://www.utdallas.edu/~pxb054000/pbrandt/Home.html">Patrick Brandt</a>,
<a href="http://www.kalevleetaru.com/">Kalev Leetaru</a>,
<a href="http://eventdata.psu.edu/">Phil Schrodt</a>, and myself about the possibility of using
<a href="http://gdelt.utdallas.edu/">GDELT</a> to examine some of
the protest activity. Much of this still remains in the discussion stage, but
some data was pulled from GDELT, and I decided to venture into the world of
map making. As a caveat, I've never really worked with geographic visualization
of data, and this is my first cut at this type of work. So, without further
ado, the map is located at <a href="http://cdb.io/14RHla0">http://cdb.io/14RHla0</a>.</p>

<h3>Data</h3>

<p>The data used to create the map contains all CAMEO codes that begin with <code>14</code>,
which is the general category for "protest" events, for the year 2013. Including
data from earlier than 2013 made the map much too cluttered.
A potential issue with the use of this CAMEO category is that it picks up governments protesting other governments, politicians protesting
policies, etc. Thus why the U.S. is blank; it was a shining beacon of protest
activity that distracted from the other parts of the map. If anyone is
interested I can put the U.S. data back in and regenerate the map. The data
was grouped by the latitude and longitude coordinates, and a count of protest
events at each location is included. If you zoom in, you are able to see the
individuals points, which when clicked provide information about the location
and number of events.</p>

<p>The main takeaway from this map seems to be that GDELT does a pretty good job
of capturing the broad trends of protest activity; the areas that are "bright"
are those that would generally be expected to be so.</p>

<h3>Note on Tools</h3>

<p>The map was created using the fantastic <a href="http://cartodb.com/">CartoDB</a> along with CSS provided
by <a href="http://www.joshuastevens.net/">Josh Stevens</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
